Elizabeth A. Drew Papers, 1946-1961
Smith College Archives
Elizabeth A. Drew Papers
1946-1961
Drew, Elizabeth A., 1887-1965
RG 42 UUID:f617d184-6829-48b3-8359-e2bd240dc847
6 boxes (2.5 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Professor of English, author, and critic. Contains biographical material, correspondence, lecture notes, and published works.
Elizabeth A. Drew was born in Singapore on December 17, 1887 and educated in England. Before her career at Smith College, she taught English at Girton College, Cambridge, England from 1916-19, and the University of Cambridge from 1934-37. She also taught in the summer at the Bread Loaf School of English in Middlebury, Vermont from 1940-46. She survived the V-2 bombings of London during World War II and soon relocated to the U.S. Shortly after arriving from England, Drew gave a lecture at Smith College, and using a letter of introduction from college dean Ada Comstock, embarked on a lecture tour. From 1946 until 1961 she was a visiting lecturer then professor in English at Smith. By her later life she had become a well-known author, critic, and lecturer, having published numerous books on poetry, modern literature, and drama. She retired from Smith in 1961 and received an honorary doctorate in letters at the 1962 Smith College Commencement. In 1963, she became a Sophia Smith Fellow. Drew died in April 1965 at the age of 77 and in her will left the college a bequest of more than $100,000 to be used by the English Department.
The collection contains biographical materials, correspondence, lecture notes, and published works. It is separated into four series as follows:
Series I: Biographical Materials
This part of the collection contains biographical materials, both personal and professional, and photographs.
Series II: Correspondence
This part of the collection consists of correspondence both personal and professional.
Series III: Notes and Lectures
The largest series of the collection, this section consists of lecture notes, as well as four books of poetry notated by Drew.
Series IV: Published Works
This part of the collection consists of books, articles, and other published writing authored by Drew.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the College Archives.
History of the Collection
The Elizabeth A. Drew Papers were donated over a period of time to the Smith College Archives from a variety of sources.
- Series I: Biographical Materials
  - Biographical Materials 1948-1965 (Box 769, Folder 1)
  - Honorary Degree 1961-1962 (Box 769, Folder 2)
  - Retirement ca. 1961 (Box 769, Folder 3)
  - Memorial Service 1965 (Box 769, Folder 4)
  - Photographs ca. 1887-1962 (Box 769, Folder 5)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Correspondence: General 1926-1963 (Box 769, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Aaron, Daniel ca. 1941 (Box 769, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Connor, George 1955-1964 (Box 769, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Eliot, T.S. 1948 (Box 769, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Richards, I.A. 1964-1965 (Box 769, Folder 10)
- Series III: Notes and Lectures
  - Lectures: Discovering Modern Poetry (2 folders) ca. 1960 (Box 770, Folder 1)
  - Notes: Literature and the Social Background undated (Box 770, Folder 2)
  - Lecture Notes: Auden (4 folders) undated (Box 770, Folder 3-6)
  - Lecture Notes: Coffee Houses undated (Box 770, Folder 7)
  - Lecture Notes: Dickens undated (Box 770, Folder 8)
  - Lecture Notes: Discovering Modern Poetry (2 folders) undated (Box 770, Folder 9-10)
  - Lecture Notes: Dylan Thomas undated (Box 770, Folder 11)
  - Lecture Notes: Eliot (3 folders) undated (Box 770, Folder 12-14)
  - Lecture Notes: Four Quarters (3 folders) undated (Box 770, Folder 15-17)
  - Lecture Notes: Freshman Poetry (6 folders) undated (Box 770, Folder 18-23)
  - Lecture Notes: Hopkins (4 folders) undated (Box 770, Folder 24-27)
  - Lecture Notes: Jane Carlyle undated (Box 770.1, Folder 1)
  - Lecture Notes: Joyce (6 folders) undated (Box 770.1, Folder 2-7)
  - Lecture Notes: Modern Drama (3 folders) undated (Box 770.1, Folder 8-10)
  - Lecture Notes: Modern Drama (4 folders) undated (Box 770.1, Folder 11-14)
  - Lecture Notes: The Novel undated (Box 770.1, Folder 15)
  - Lecture Notes: The Novel (3 folders) undated (Box 770.1, Folder 16-18)
  - Lecture Notes: The Novel II (3 folders) undated (Box 770.1, Folder 19-21)
  - Lecture Notes: Novel 211 (4 folders) undated (Box 770.1, Folder 22-25)
  - Lecture Notes: Pepys Diary undated (Box 770.1, Folder 26)
  - Lecture Notes: Poetry 211 (4 folders) undated (Box 770.1, Folder 27-30)
  - Lecture Notes: Shakespeare Sonnet undated (Box 771, Folder 1)
  - Lecture Notes: Shakespearean Sonnet undated (Box 771, Folder 2)
  - Lecture Notes: Sweeney Among the Nightingales undated (Box 771, Folder 3)
  - Lecture Notes: Thomas Hardy undated (Box 771, Folder 4)
  - Lecture Notes: Thomas Love Peacock undated (Box 771, Folder 5)
  - Lecture Notes: Yeats (5 folders) undated (Box 771, Folder 6-10)
  - Lecture Notes: Untitled (5 folders) undated (Box 771, Folder 11-15)
  - Lecture Notes: Untitled (4 folders) undated (Box 771, Folder 16-19)
  - Lecture Notes: Untitled (2 folders) undated (Box 771, Folder 20-21)
  - Yale University Notebook I: Contemporary Poetry undated (Box 771.1, Folder 1)
  - Yale University Notebook II undated (Box 771.1, Folder 2)
  - Yale University Notebook III undated (Box 771.1, Folder 3)
  - Yale University Notebook IV: Poetry and Society undated (Box 771.1, Folder 4)
- Series IV: Published Works
  - "A Hundred Years Ago" undated (Box 771.1, Folder 5)
  - Jonathan Swift undated (Box 771.1, Folder 6)
  - "The Library of Lady Mary Wortley Montag" 1934 (Box 771.1, Folder 7)
  - "Life and Art in the Novel" 1962 (Box 771.1, Folder 8)
  - "Literature in College" undated (Box 771.1, Folder 9)
  - The Literature of Gossip (6 folders) undated (Box 771.1, Folder 10-15)
  - The Literature of Gossip (5 folders) undated (Box 772, Folder 1-5)
  - "Mother and Daughter" undated (Box 772, Folder 6)
  - "Novels by Hamlet with a Camera" 1941 (Box 772, Folder 7)
  - "Poetic Patterns: A Note on Versification" 1956 (Box 772, Folder 8)
  - "Poetry and Existence" undated (Box 772, Folder 9)
  - "The Relationship of Form to Content in the Poetry of W.H. Auden" (2 folders) undated (Box 772, Folder 10-11)
  - "Salad Days" undated (Box 772, Folder 12)
  - "Salve for the Servantless" undated (Box 772, Folder 13)
  - "Shakespeare and All That" 1935 (Box 772, Folder 14)
  - "Wanted: New Myths for Writers" 1941 (Box 772, Folder 15)
  - Reviews of Published Works 1959-1965 (Box 772, Folder 16)
  - Speeches undated (Box 772, Folder 17)
  - Commencement address at Bread Loaf School of English 1953 (Box 772, Folder 18)
  - Robert Frost dinner 1954 (Box 772, Folder 19)
  - Book: Collected Poems of W. B. Yeats 1951 (Box 772)
  - Book: Collected Poems 1909-1935 T. S. Eliot 1935 (Box 772)
  - Book: Four Quarters undated (Box 772)
  - Book: Poems 1940-1947 Theodore Spencer 1948 (Box 772)